Karl Fenning Papers 074
People's Archive, MLK Library
Karl Fenning Papers
1881-1962
People's Archive, MLK Library
Fenning, Karl, 1881-1963
074
4.5 Linear feet
4 Boxes
Arrangement
Series 1: Professional Papers This series is made up of correspondence relating to professional activities and teaching, professional publications, clippings, and biographical materials. Series 2: Personal Papers This series consists of educational records, correspondence and research concerning Karl Fenning's ancestry, and papers relating to his wife, Hazel O'Neil Fenning, brother Frederick A. Fenning, and mother, Annie Dey Fenning. This series also contains general correspondence, including a letter from Carrie J. Kingdon (possibly Karl's aunt or cousin), who was vacationing in Switzerland at the outbreak of World War I. Series 3: Photographs This series includes photos of Karl Fenning at various ages. Also included are family photographs, Karl Fenning's birthplace, and images taken in Washington, D.C., New Jersey, Florida, Boston, and Yosemite National Park. Series 4: Ephemera This series includes the baby book of Karl's niece, Katherine Hine Fenning, 2 leather wallets, a Metropolitan Police Department badge, a passport issued to Fenning in 1916, and various personal and professional certificates.
Biographical / Historical
Karl Fenning was born in Washington, D.C., on March 30, 1881, the only child of James and Annie Dey Fenning (he had an older, half brother, Frederick A. Fenning). He attended Central High School in the District, and later Trinity College in Hartford, Connecticut, where he earned a bachelor's degree in 1903. He then returned to Washington to attend law school at National University and Columbian College (now George Washington University). Fenning practiced law in Washington from 1904-1906, in New York City from 1906-1911, and in Cleveland, Ohio from 1911-1921. On June 7, 1917, he married Hazel O'Neil. In 1921, President Warren Harding appointed Fenning Assistant Commissioner of Patents, and in 1925, he was appointed Special Assistant to the Attorney General, a position in which he served until 1928. From 1923 until 1946, Fenning was a professor of patent law at Georgetown University. He died February 28, 1963 in Washington.
Custodial History
Frederick F. Wright, grandnephew of Karl Fenning, donated the collection to the Library in July 2006, with subsequent donations in September 2006.
Related Materials
Lemon and Mary Hine Correspondence Collection (Collection 076)
Scope and Contents
The collection consists of personal and professional correspondence, professional publications, clippings, genealogical and biographical information, memorabilia and family photographs. The materials are divided into four series: Professional Papers, Personal Papers, Photographs, and Ephemera.
Photographs; Correspondence; Genealogy; Ephemera; College teachers; Lawyers; United States--Officials and employees
- Series 1: Professional Papers
  Scope and Contents
  This series is made up of correspondence relating to professional activities and teaching, professional publications, clippings, and biographical materials.
  - Biography, Undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - General Correspondence, 1903-1925 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - General Correspondence, 1926-1962 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Department of Agriculture Appointments, 1900-1901 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Department of the Interior Appointments, 1902 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Clippings, 1904, 1917, 1921 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Publications: "A Neglected Well of Information" Scientific American, 1924 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - "Patent Office" Chemical Age, 1924 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Teaching and Lectures: Correspondence, 1925-1926 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Teaching and Lectures: Correspondence, 1932, 1947-1948 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Civil Service Application, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - General Professional Papers, 1908 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Series 2: Personal Papers
  Series II consists of educational records, correspondence and research concerning Karl Fenning's ancestry, and papers relating to his wife, Hazel O'Neil Fenning, brother Frederick A. Fenning, and mother, Annie Dey Fenning. This series also contains general correspondence, including a letter from Carrie J. Kingdon (possibly Karl's aunt or cousin), who was vacationing in Switzerland at the outbreak of World War I.
  - General Correspondence, 1898-1926, 1948, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - General Correspondence - Carrie J. Kingdon to Karl Fenning, November 1914 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Trinity College, 1899-1905 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Trinity College: Phi Gamma Delta, 1901-1904, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Law School, 1903-1905 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Property, 1917 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Family: Ancestry, 1899-1942 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Family: Ancestry Correspondence, 1899-1942 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Family: Hazel Fenning, 1917, 1936, 1939 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Family: Frederick A. Fenning, 1907, 1936, 1944, 1964 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Baby Book of Katherine Hine Fenning, 1902 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Family: Annie Dey Fenning - Sketchbook, 1870 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Family: Annie Dey Fenning, 1921 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - General Personal Papers, Undated (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - General Personal Papers, Undated (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Memorabilia, Undated (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Series 3: Photographs
  This series includes photos of Karl Fenning at various ages. Also included are family photos, Karl Fenning's birthplace, and images taken in the Washington, DC area, New Jersey, Florida, Boston, and Yosemite.
  - Childhood, 1882-1900 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Trinity College Commencement, 1903 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Fenning and Family, 1912 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Patent Office Photograph, 1925 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - House, Undated (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Woman, 1919 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Postcard: Huguenot Memorial Church - Pelham Manor NY, Undated (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - House - Woman - Man, Undated (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Framed Photo of Katherine Hine Fenning, 1910 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Adirondacks, 1901 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Harper Ferry - Train Scene, 1904 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Karl Fenning, 1896 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Karl Fenning, 1904 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Karl Fenning - Trinity College Commencement, 1903 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Karl Fenning, 1900 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Karl Fenning (more likely Frederick Fenning), Undated (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Karl Fenning's birthplace - interior and exterior, 1881 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Karl Fenning and Annie Dey Fenning - framed, 1905 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Karl Fenning - framed, 1908 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Annie Fenning - framed, 1900 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Mother of Annie Fenning (?) - framed, Undated (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Photo Album - DC Area - Mt. Vernon, 1900 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Photo Album - Trinity College - Yosemite - Summer Jobs - DC Area - Hazel O'Neil Fenning, 1910-1925 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - House, Undated (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Building, Undated (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Man - dog - house, Undated (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Annie Fenning - Asbury Park NJ, 1907 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Mirror Lake - Yosemite, Undated (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Washington DC scenes, Undated (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - The New Lucerne Hotel Booklet, 1912-1913 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Thomas Brokaw - Orlando FL, 1914 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Karl and Annie Fenning - Orlando, 1914 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - D.K. Dey, October 1906 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Postcard: to Annie Fenning from Carrie J. Kingdon - 13 Brainard St. Mt. Holly NJ, 1909 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Thomas Brokaw - woman - house, Undated (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Mr. and Mrs. Thomas Brokaw, 1919 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Photographs: Katherine Fenning, 1902-1912 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Photograph: Katherine Fenning, 1902-1912 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Photograph: Karl Fenning and 6 men, 1903 (Box 4, Folder 2)
- Series 4: Ephemera
  Series IV includes the baby book of Karl's niece, Katherine Hine Fenning, 2 leather wallets, a Metropolitan Police Badge, a passport issued to Fenning in 1916, and various personal and professional certificates.
  - Baby book of Katherine Hine Fenning, 1902 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Certificate - Admitted to Practice Law in Ohio, 1911 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Certificate - Member - Ohio Sons of the American Revolution, 1912 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Certificate - Appointed Scoutmaster - Boy Scouts of America, 1913 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Certificate - Admitted - Attorney and Counselor - US Court of Appeals - Sixth Circuit, 1916 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Certificate - Admitted - Attorney and Counselor - Supreme Court of the United States, 1925 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Certificate - Member - American Arbitration Association - National Panel of Arbitrators, 1941 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Passport - Karl Fenning, 1916 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Metropolitan Police Department Badge, Undated (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Wallet, labeled KHF, Undated (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Wallet - Trinity Senior Prom, 1903 (Box 4, Folder 13)